I think it's coming together.
開始有點樣子了呢
Akira, since your hair is short,
輝，因為你是短髮
we'll start by adding extensions for volume
我們就透過接髮的方式
and sew them into your natural hair with an extension hook.
用鉤針將假髮連在你原本的頭髮上
Finally, we'll secure them by weaving in any loose strands, and you're done!
最後再把鬆散的髮束編好，就完成了
Starting today, I'm…
從今天開始，我就有一頭…
Farmer Dreadlocks!
雷鬼辮啦
5. TRY OUT DREADLOCKS
（五：綁雷鬼辮）
I see. So you worked at a specialty salon for over ten years?
原來妳在專業髮廊 已經工作了十年了？
Yes, I was totally devoted to dreadlocks.
是的，我的專長是雷鬼辮
So when I heard that Akira wanted dreadlocks, I just had to help him out.
所以當我聽到輝想綁雷鬼辮的時候 就想說一定要幫忙
I taught at a college in Tokyo.
我在東京一間大學任教
I was a makeup artist for films.
我是電影化妝師
Wow! Films? What did you work on?
電影啊？妳參與過哪些電影？
Let's see.
我想想
I did this one. Do you know it?
這部就是我做的，你知道嗎？
I've seen this one! It was made in Japan?
我看過這部，這是在日本拍的？
That's right!
沒錯
We were filming the sequel and…
我們原本在拍續集，結果…
We were filming the sequel until that day.
我們原本在拍續集，直到爆發的那天
You'd never expect to be attacked by real zombies
誰能想到在拍殭屍電影的時候
while filming a zombie movie.
居然會遭到真的殭屍攻擊
We took too long to notice.
我們太慢才發現
And so…
所以…
Mr. Nakayama, you're so convincing!
中山先生，你演得真是逼真呀
So much happened along the way here.
來這裡的一路上發生了好多事
But everyone in the village welcomed us with open arms.
但是村子裡的人都張開雙臂歡迎我們
I can't thank them enough for their kindness.
又對我們好親切，我衷心感謝他們
And so, though it's just wishful thinking for now,
所以，雖然是我一廂情願
I'd like to continue living in this village.
我還是希望能繼續住在村子裡 過著現在的生活
That's how I truly feel.
這是我內心的真實感受
You're right!
沒錯
Thanks.
真是謝謝妳
It must be tough doing work you're unaccustomed to.
妳不習慣做這些事，一定很辛苦吧
Not at all.
不會
The key to keeping this village safe from zombies
維護村子不受殭屍襲擊的關鍵
might come from using skills from a time without electricity.
也許就是要透過這些 沒有電力時代的生存技能
I'm very interested in how people live here.
我對這裡的生活方式很有興趣
Well, I don't really get it, but nothing beats rice cooked on a hearth.
我聽不懂啦 但還是用爐子煮的米飯最好吃
Add plenty of water and place it on a roaring fire for the perfect rice.
要加很多水，放在熊熊大火上 才能煮出最完美的米飯
I see.
原來是這樣
I guess all that extra effort makes it taste even better.
看來就是那多一分努力 讓飯變得更美味
Very interes--
真是有意思的…
-Akemi! -No!
-明美！ -不要！
Cut it out, Old Man Hiko!
別鬧了，彥老爹
You left me all alone! Where have you been all this time?
妳丟下我一個人，跑去哪裡了？
Sorry about that.
真是抱歉
He's been that way ever since his old lady passed away.
自從他老婆死了之後 就變成這副德行了
I see.
這樣啊…
-Akemi! Is dinner ready yet? -He may not look it,
-明美，晚餐好了嗎？ -別看他這樣
but he used to be the best hunter in this village.
他以前可是這村裡最厲害的獵人
Hey, Tome.
留
Have any rope or something you can spare?
妳有沒有繩子還是什麼可以包紮？
I was haying and sliced myself with the scythe.
我割草的時候被鐮刀劃傷了
How terrible! I'll get you some right away.
太糟糕了，我馬上去幫你拿
Try not to bind it too tightly or you'll risk necrosis of the tissue.
不要包太緊 否則可能會造成組織壞死
First, raise the injury above your heart and after applying pressure to the area,
先把傷口抬到高於心臟的地方 然後用力壓住
then try applying pressure to the artery.
接著壓住動脈
You seem to know a lot about this. Are you a doctor?
妳懂很多呢，妳是醫生嗎？
No.
不是
When I was little, I was interested in medicine, so I did some reading on it.
我小時候對醫學很有興趣 所以看過一些書
What's this? A doctor?
什麼？有醫生嗎？
My back has been feeling worse than usual since this morning.
我的背從一早開始就比往常更痛
Like I said--
我剛剛說了…
What a young and beautiful doctor!
真是年輕貌美的醫生啊
I stumbled and hurt my knee.
我跌倒了，膝蓋好痛啊
My stomach isn't feeling good.
我的胃不太舒服
-I can't control my bladder. -I'm constipated.
-我膀胱虛弱 -我便祕
Akemi!
明美！
No!
不要！
-I heard she's a doctor. -How wonderful.
-聽說她是醫生 -太棒了
Is that what I think it is?
那是我想的那個東西嗎？
Is this a cesspit?
這是糞坑嗎？
You don't see them being used much nowadays,
這種東西現在已經很少見了
but it's a great source for natural fertilizer.
但這是很棒的天然肥料來源
Fertilizer?
肥料？
In Japan, the rain washes away a lot of the minerals from our fields.
在日本，雨水會沖掉 田裡的大量礦物質
But if we recycle the food that we eat by returning it to the soil,
但是只要讓我們吃下去的食物 回到土裡進行回收循環
we can replenish those minerals.
就能補充那些礦物質
I see.
原來如此
They say a dive in the cesspit will get you ahead in life.
據說掉進糞坑的人就能成功
Want to give it a try, young man?
想試試看嗎，年輕人？
Who is that girl?
那個女孩是誰？
She escaped from the city.
她是從城市逃到這裡來的
She lost her parents and that dog is the only family she has left.
她失去了雙親 只剩下那隻狗相依為命
I haven't seen her smile once since she got here.
從她來到這裡後 我還沒見過她的笑容
Such a young girl. Poor thing.
年紀還這麼輕，真是可憐
Hey there, beautiful lady.
妳好呀，小美女
I'm trying to become a comedian, so I'm practicing my juggling.
我想成為喜劇演員 所以正在練習雜耍
Would you care to watch?
妳想看嗎？
Why are you using daruma?
為什麼要用不倒翁？
Why? Because Gunma is known for their daruma.
為什麼啊？ 因為群馬的不倒翁很有名呀
Once I've perfected this, I want to perform it naked.
等我駕輕就熟後，我想要裸體表演
I'll be juggling so fast that you won't see my crotch. So don't worry!
我會動作快到讓人看不見 我的小弟弟，所以不用擔心
Are you into little girls or something?
大哥哥，你該不會是蘿莉控吧？
Why are you even talking to me?
為什麼要跟我說話？
It's common courtesy to say hello to a lady,
跟女士打招呼是基本禮儀
whether they're a girl or an old woman.
不論對方是小女孩還是老太太
Courtesy?
禮儀？
That's right!
沒錯
In Italy, you never forget to smile at women,
在義大利看到女士一定要微笑
and it's considered rude if you don't compliment women.
不好好讚美女性可是很無禮的
You're so strange, Mister. You're not even Italian.
你好奇怪喔，大哥哥 你又不是義大利人
Looks like I finally got you to smile.
看來我終於成功逗妳笑了
I'm Kencho! What's your name, beautiful lady?
我是憲一，小美女，妳叫什麼名字？
Anju. And this is Charo.
我叫杏樹，這是茶六
Then I'll call you Angie!
那我就叫妳杏杏吧
Hey, could you watch me practice my other acts?
妳願意看我練習其他戲法嗎？
There's one where I eat udon with my butt!
我要用屁股吃烏龍麵
-I'll pass. -What?
-先不用 -什麼？
Wunderbar!
好棒
What a magnificent water wheel!
這個水車真是壯觀！
It's one of those hydroelectric ones.
這是用來水力發電的
It produces the minimum amount of electricity we need.
可以產生我們所需的最低電量
Renewable energy.
可再生能源
It's perfect for Nippon with its abundant sources of water!
對於水資源充沛的日本來說 真是再完美不過
Zombie bears and zombie boars have been showing up in this area,
這個地區有時會 出現殭屍熊和殭屍野豬
so we've fortified our electrical fence to keep them out.
所以我們加強了電籬笆，好阻擋野獸
That's also powered by this.
那也是靠這個發電的
I see.
原來如此
That said, this only gives you a small shock if you touch it.
雖然如此 就算碰到也只有輕微電流而已
By the way…
對了
Bea, make sure you don't touch this.
貝兒，千萬不要碰這個
-What is it? -It's an earth-leakage circuit breaker.
-那是什麼？ -這是漏電斷路器
It shuts off the power if there's an electric leak
如果電壓過高造成漏電
from the voltage being cranked up too high.
這就會切斷電力
It's dangerous, so you mustn't touch it.
非常危險，所以千萬別碰
Ja! Understood!
好的，我瞭解了
Since living in this village,
自從在村子裡住下來之後
I've started thinking about connections between people.
我就開始思考人和人之間的連結
Doing anything here takes time.
在這裡做什麼都需要費工夫
You can't survive unless you help one another
所以大家要互相幫忙才能生存下去
because things aren't convenient.
正因為這裡不是太便利
It helps connect people.
反而能把大家連結起來
Here, you can see the work that needs to be done,
在這裡，可以看到有哪些事要做
and you see the people who do it.
也能看見做這些事的人
Unlike in the city, things are limited here.
這裡跟城市不一樣，有很多限制
Because they are limited, I'm thankful and happy for whatever I can get.
或許就是因為資源有限 才讓大家更覺得幸福
That's kinda what it feels like!
就是這種感覺
Hey, Akira!
輝！
-Good job! -Kencho!
-好樣的 -憲一
-You've been working the fields all day? -Yeah. What about you?
-你整天都在田裡忙嗎？ -是啊，你呢？
I slaughtered a chicken!
我宰了一隻雞
I may never eat chicken again because of the trauma.
那創傷讓我永遠不想再吃雞肉了
I know, right?
就是說啊
Isn't that guy…
那傢伙不是…
Higurashi?
日暮嗎？
Hey, Higurashi!
日暮！
You're still alive too?
你也還活著啊？
It's me! Ryuzaki!
是我，龍崎啊
It's been a while.
好久不見了
What? He left.
什麼？他竟然走了
-Who's Higurashi? -Don't you remember?
-日暮是誰啊？ -你不記得了嗎？
He was in our general education classes at K University.
他是我們在Ｋ大通識課的同學呀
He stopped showing up after about six months
他開學大約半年後就沒來了
Heard a rumor he became a NEET.
聽說他變成了尼特族
Didn't expect to run into him here.
沒想到竟然會在這裡遇到他
Of all the damn people to run into…
為什麼偏偏讓我遇到他們…
Damn it.
可惡
It's been a while since I've seen their annoying faces.
好久沒看到那兩張惹人厭的臉了
They always looked like they were having so much fun by themselves.
他們每次都自顧自地 一副玩得很開心的樣子
Perfect. This is perfect.
很好，太好了
Hey, Dad!
爸
You wanna have a drink together?
想一起喝一杯嗎？
Sure. Don't see why not.
好啊，有何不可
What better way to give back to your dad than sharing a drink together!
還有什麼比陪爸爸喝一杯 更棒的孝行呢？
Hold on.
等等
Have Dad's hands always been so thin?
爸的手一直都這麼纖細嗎？
Looking closely, he's gotten more grey.
仔細一看，他的白髮也變多了
After not seeing him for a while, seems like he got smaller too.
一陣子沒看到他 似乎也變得更嬌小了
Hey, Dad.
爸
What is it?
什麼事？
After coming back to the village, I've been thinking…
回來村子後，我一直在想…
When I was a kid, I idolized the big city, but living here is not that bad.
小時候的我很嚮往大城市 但是住在這裡也沒那麼糟
Besides, it must be tough working that big field all by yourself.
況且一個人顧這麼大一塊田地 一定很辛苦吧
I'm sure Mom could use the extra help too.
有人幫忙的話媽媽一定也很開心
So I…
所以我…
What's the point in staying cooped up in this small village?
窩在這個小村子裡有什麼用？
A man follows his dream, the biggest one he can dream of.
男人就該追夢，夢想越大越好
What the hell?
什麼啊？
I was trying to repay you both.
我是想要回來孝順你們呀
You talk big, but you're just a country farmer…
你說這些大話 但你也只是個鄉下農夫…
What was your dream as a kid?
爸，你小時候的夢想是什麼？
Akira,
輝
haven't you ever wanted to see Earth from the far reaches of space?
你沒想過要從太空看看地球嗎？
Space?
太空？
Apparently, seeing our planet from outer space is shocking to people.
據說從外太空看到自己的星球 會讓人類的腦袋受到很大的衝擊
Once you leave school and become an adult, you realize how small your world was.
從學校畢業，出了社會後 你才會明白自己的世界有多小
Same as how you left the village for Tokyo.
就像你離開村子去東京一樣
It made you realize how small your world was.
才能明白自己的世界原來這麼渺小
Looking at the world from space,
從太空看地球…
you don't see the equator line or the lines that divide countries.
你看不到赤道也看不到國界
You see how tiny your existence is and that moves you.
你會明白自己的存在多麼微不足道 而深受感動
Your existence on a tiny planet, in the vastness of space…
你在如此浩瀚的太空中 只是存在於一顆小行星上
To tell you the truth,
老實跟你說
ever since I was a kid, I've wanted to be an astronaut!
我從小就想當太空人
What?
什麼？
Well, I'm just too dumb, so there's no way that will happen at this point!
但我實在太笨了，所以早就來不及了
What the hell?
什麼啊？
I had no idea you were such a joker!
我都不曉得你這麼愛開玩笑
Yeah.
是啊
Compared to 13.8 billion years in the history of space,
跟宇宙138億年的歷史相比
eighty years of life isn't even a tenth of a second.
80年只不過是瞬間的事
So don't sell yourself short.
所以別小看自己
Find your dream, Akira. Biggest one you can.
找到你的夢想，輝，越大越好
A man without a dream is nothing more than a jellyfish.
沒有夢想的男人，就跟水母沒有兩樣
By the way Akira, not that it matters,
對了，輝，雖然這沒什麼
but that hair doesn't look good on you at all.
但是這個髮型實在不適合你
Shut up!
閉嘴啦
I wanted them!
我就是想要
31. GO HOME AND SPEND TIME WITH MY PARENTS
（31：回家陪伴父母）
Sorry to keep you zombies waiting.
真抱歉，讓你們這些殭屍久等了
Are you ready?
你們準備好了嗎？
-Yes. -Yeah.
-好了
The plan is simple.
計畫很簡單
35. F*CK UP SOCIETY
（37：破壞社會）
Turn everyone in the village into zombie food!
把村子裡的所有人 都變成殭屍的食物吧
Might as well get revenge on those normies too.
順便報復那些現充
Just you wait, Akira.
等著吧，輝
Hey, how many times do I have to remind you?
要我提醒你多少遍？
That's not a bathroom…
不可以在那裡上…
What is it?
怎麼了？
Over there.
那裡
What's the matter, Shizuka?
怎麼了，閑？
-Dad. -Yeah.
-爸 -對
What the hell is going on here?
這裡發生了什麼事？
Akira!
輝
Leave your mother to me and go to your friends.
媽媽交給我，去找你朋友
What? Dad?!
什麼？爸？
Your friends have supported you all the way here, right?
你朋友一路陪著你到這裡來
Keep them safe.
你要保護好他們
They're running so fast! This is hilarious!
他們跑好快，太搞笑了
Get the sick ones inside first!
先把老人家帶進去
Lock the door and barricade it the best you can!
把門鎖上，盡量堵好
Are you all right, Shizuka?
閑，妳沒事吧？
Yes.
沒事
Hunting Club! Forward!
獵友會，前進！
Fire!
開槍
It's no good!
沒用
-There are too many! -Let's fall back.
-太多了 -撤退
This way!
往這裡
What's this? Going home already?
怎麼了？這麼早就要回家啦？
The night is still young, you know.
時間還早呢
Let's play outside a little longer.
我們在外頭多玩一會兒吧
5. BLOW SOMETHING UP WITH DYNAMITE
（五：引爆炸藥）
3. FIRE A REAL GUN
（三：開真槍）
This is so horrible.
這太過分了
I have to do something.
我得做些什麼
If this keeps up, the village will be destroyed.
繼續這樣下去，村子會被毀掉的
Thanks for the save, Bea!
謝謝救援，貝兒
No problem!
沒問題
-Kencho! -Beatrix!
-憲一 -貝兒翠絲
Thank goodness! You're all okay!
謝天謝地，你們都沒事
We'll talk later!
晚點再聊
We must get everyone in the village out of here now.
我們必須先把所有村民撤走
Get everyone to the suspension bridge!
帶大家到吊橋去
But there's an electric fence around the village.
但是村子周圍有電籬笆
It's just meant to deter zombie boars, so the voltage shouldn't be dangerous.
那只是用來嚇阻殭屍野豬的 電壓應該不危險
Really?
真的嗎？
He's getting shocked pretty badly!
他被電得很慘耶
To save someone from electrocution,
要幫助觸電的人
we need a non-conductive material like wood
就要用像木頭這種不導電的材質
to knock them away!
用力把他打飛就對了
I knew you could do it, Shizuka!
我就知道妳一定會，閑
That was a close one.
剛剛真是驚險
But why is the voltage so high?
但是為什麼電壓這麼高？
Could it be?
難道是？
Did someone increase the voltage
會不會有人調高電壓
and disable the earth-leakage circuit breaker?
關閉了漏電斷路器？
Hold on a second!
等等
So then the same electric fence that protects the village
所以用來保護村民 把殭屍擋在外面的電籬笆
from zombies is trapping us in?
卻把我們困在裡面了？
Hey!
喂！
Akira! Ryuzaki!
輝、龍崎！
As expected, you guys sure are persistent!
你們真是一如所料非常頑強啊
Higurashi?
日暮？
Hey! There are zombies behind you!
你後面有殭屍
Hey, they're coming!
他們快來了
That guy is an idiot.
那傢伙真是個蠢蛋
I can't believe he still hasn't figured it out.
我不敢相信他竟然還沒搞清楚
No way.
不會吧
You guys did this?
這是你們幹的？
That's correct!
沒錯
Why in the world would you do this?
你到底為什麼要這麼做？
Well, we're all gonna be zombies one day.
反正我們終究都會成為殭屍的
It'd be a shame if I didn't get to do what I wanted before, right?
要是在那之前沒能做到想做的事 就太可惜了，對吧？
That notebook…
那本筆記本…
What? Were you making a list too?
怎麼？你也在列清單嗎？
35. F*CK UP SOCIETY
（37：破壞社會）
What a coincidence!
真巧啊
What should I do next?
接下來該做什麼呢？
Yeah, gotta be this one.
對，就是這一項
Akira, I'd love to see you become a zombie with my own eyes.
輝，我想親眼看著你變成殭屍
Screw you! What did Akira do to you anyway?
去你的，輝有對你怎樣嗎？
I've hated you since the moment we met in college.
自從我們在大學認識後 我就超討厭你們
You didn't have a care in the world.
你們看起來成天無憂無慮
Enjoying life, each and every day.
每天只顧著享受生活
I couldn't help but be disgusted.
讓我感到無比噁心
That's your reason?
就為了這個理由？
This is our last summer break ever.
這是我們人生的最後一個暑假
What's wrong with enjoying it like you guys?
跟你們一樣好好享受哪裡錯了？
-You bastard. -You only live once.
-混帳東西 -人生只有一回
So enjoy life the way you want to.
所以要照你的意思享受生活
I get it because I'm doing that too.
我明白，因為我也正在這麼做
Akira, what are you say--
輝，你在說什…
If you're gonna put your freedom first, you need to respect others' freedoms too.
但如果你要把自己的自由擺第一 那麼也該尊重其他人的自由
Stealing freedom from the villagers who are struggling to survive…
剝奪那些 好不容易活下來的村民的自由
That's what you want to do?
就是你想做的事？
I seriously don't understand what you're saying.
我完全不明白你在胡說八道什麼
Our bucket lists are nothing alike!
別把我的願望清單跟你的相提並論
I still haven't repaid my parents for raising me.
我還沒報答父母的養育之恩
If I have to live with the regret of not giving back to my parents,
如果要我帶著 無法回報父母的悔恨活下去
I'd rather be eaten by zombies!
我寧願被殭屍吃掉算了！
Nice.
很好
That's what I want to hear!
我就想聽到這個
It'll be a competition between you and me to see who finishes their list first.
我們就來比賽吧，看誰能先完成清單
Akira, we'll be surrounded by zombies at this rate!
輝，再這樣下去 我們會被殭屍包圍的
It's frustrating, but we must retreat!
雖然不甘願，但是我們得撤退了
We need to evacuate everyone in the village!
我們得疏散村裡所有人
Charo?
茶六？
I'll go to the water wheel shed!
我去水車小屋
I'll shut the generator powering the electrical fence!
關閉電籬笆的發電機！
Then I'm going to give back to my parents!
那我去回報父母了
Your goal seems to be different from everyone else, but whatever.
你的目標一直都跟其他人不太一樣 但是隨便啦
We need to get everyone else.
我們得去找其他人
Once the fence shuts off, let's meet at the mountain bridge.
籬笆斷電後，我們到吊橋會合
Okay!
好
Angie, don't leave my side, okay?
杏杏，妳要跟好，知道嗎？
Angie!
杏杏！
Kencho! Over there!
憲一，在那裡！
What is she doing over there?
她跑到那裡做什麼？
Leave her to me!
交給我吧
You go to your mom!
你快去找你媽
But…
但是…
We're definitely going to make it out of this alive.
我們絕對會活著出去的
Yeah!
好！
Is she going to stop the water wheel?
她要去停下水車嗎？
Not on my watch!
有我在就別想
Go have fun, however you want.
就照你們的意思好好玩吧
Let's drag out the villagers hiding in their homes
我們把躲在家中的村民全拖出來
and turn every last one of them into zombie food.
讓所有人變成餵殭屍的飼料
A game of tag and then hide-and-seek.
來場鬼抓人兼捉迷藏
That's a pretty good start to summer break!
暑假就是要這樣才夠讚
Next Time: Hometown of the Dead II.
下一集：死者的家鄉-中